<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Michael is coding - Career</title><link href="https://michaeliscoding.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://michaeliscoding.com/feeds/career.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://michaeliscoding.com/</id><updated>2023-01-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated><subtitle>Learn to write fast, beautiful and efficient code. Understand programming concepts and technologies. Advance your career by learning how to deal with people.</subtitle><entry><title>8 skills you need to become a Remote $100k+ dev</title><link href="https://michaeliscoding.com/8-skills-you-need-to-become-remote-100k-dev/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-01-21T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-01-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Michael</name></author><id>tag:michaeliscoding.com,2023-01-21:/8-skills-you-need-to-become-remote-100k-dev/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Knowing how to code is not enough for a great dev career.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="8 skills you need to become a Remote $100k dev" src="https://michaeliscoding.com/images/0031-remote-100k-dev-skills.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's just the first step.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You need more skills to become a senior or lead dev with more impact, money and choices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="1-master-coding"&gt;1. Master coding&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#1-master-coding" title="Permanent link"&gt;Permalink&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coding is not enough, but it is a prerequisite. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You need to master coding and have a lot of hands-on experience  so you can:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Offer multiple solutions to the problem at hand&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Evaluate other people's code and suggest improvements&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spot potential problems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Optimise code&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fix issues&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="2-learn-related-technologies"&gt;2. Learn related technologies&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#2-learn-related-technologies" title="Permanent link"&gt;Permalink&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Code doesn't exist in a vacuum. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More often than not, you'll need to use multiple technologies to solve the problem at hand. Must haves these days:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Git &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some DB (start with SQL)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basics of networks (at least HTTP)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other technologies you can choose depending on your interests:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Frameworks (e.g. Django, Rails, React etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Docker&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cloud environments(AWS,  GCP, Azure)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And so on and so on&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's different for everybody; this is where you can create your unique combination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="3-communication-presentation-skills"&gt;3. Communication &amp;amp; presentation skills&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#3-communication-presentation-skills" title="Permanent link"&gt;Permalink&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clear communication is a must, especially in writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have to be able to clearly explain yourself -  your ideas, challenges and problems - to a wide variety of people: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Developers, &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Managers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Customers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Explaining things in terms of value for the business or great technical detail, depending on who you talk to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="4-estimating"&gt;4. Estimating&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#4-estimating" title="Permanent link"&gt;Permalink&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You need to be able to estimate work so you can plan. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It doesn't need to be perfect, but it needs to be good enough so the business or your manager doesn't get bad surprises. You'll also get estimates from others, and you need to know if they make sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You need to ask the right questions to check if their estimations are solid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="5-planning-time-management"&gt;5. Planning &amp;amp; time management&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#5-planning-time-management" title="Permanent link"&gt;Permalink&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You need to be able to take over a big chunk of work and:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Break it down into smaller pieces &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plan how it will be done&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By who &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Manage other people's time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;So everything works well, and you deliver&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="6-leadership-management"&gt;6. Leadership &amp;amp; Management&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#6-leadership-management" title="Permanent link"&gt;Permalink&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You need to be able to lead and manage other people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That means:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Motivating them&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Giving them proper feedback&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep them happy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Watch team dynamics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Organise them into teams &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Setup  the appropriate structure &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assign responsibilities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="7-hiring-building-teams"&gt;7. Hiring &amp;amp; building teams&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#7-hiring-building-teams" title="Permanent link"&gt;Permalink&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being able to pick and hire the right people is a superpower. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People make or break a business. If you can choose great people, they'll make your job much easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="8-negotiation"&gt;8. Negotiation&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#8-negotiation" title="Permanent link"&gt;Permalink&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The better negotiator you are, the more money you get. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It might not be nice, but it's true. Your salary depends on your negotiation skills.
You need to be able to sell yourself, explain what you can bring to the business and employ the right tactics to get what you're worth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#conclusion" title="Permanent link"&gt;Permalink&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don't have to master all of the skills above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it would be best if you learned them to some extent. People have different strengths and weaknesses, and so do you. Over time you'll find which of the above comes naturally to you and which you need to learn more intentionally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on that, your career might be more technical or more managerial as you see fit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It will not take a year, but you'll get there if you do the work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll be going deeper into each of the above, so subscribe to the newsletter and follow me on Twitter if you want to dig deeper.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Career"></category><category term="career"></category><category term="skills"></category></entry><entry><title>How I got a remote €130k+ job</title><link href="https://michaeliscoding.com/how-i-got-remote-130k-job/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-01-18T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-01-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Michael</name></author><id>tag:michaeliscoding.com,2023-01-18:/how-i-got-remote-130k-job/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In October 2022, I was fired from my remote €100k+ job. I got a new remote €130k+ job in December. This is how:&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Remote €130k+ job" src="https://michaeliscoding.com/images/0030-remote-130k-job.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="fired"&gt;Fired!&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#fired" title="Permanent link"&gt;Permalink&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our company was raising series B investments. One evening I got a work email saying there'll be a company-wide meeting the following day. At that meeting, the founders announced that the company didn't get money from investors and would talk to everyone individually during the day. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Three hours later, I was fired after over 6 years at this company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was employee no.3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was pretty devastating. I didn't expect I'd be one to let go. After a tough day and a few drinks in the evening, I started to look for a new job the following day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="contacting-people-i-know"&gt;Contacting people I know&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#contacting-people-i-know" title="Permanent link"&gt;Permalink&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I reached out to my contacts. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I send emails telling them I'm looking for a new job and send them an updated CV. You never know who can help you. It's no shame to be looking for a new job. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="linkedin"&gt;LinkedIn&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#linkedin" title="Permanent link"&gt;Permalink&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second I checked my LinkedIn profile and did some cleanup. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I focused on describing things I accomplished that are interesting and in demand. I changed my settings so recruiters can see I'm open to work. After that, I went to LinkedIn Jobs and started to search and apply. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I searched for remote UK jobs as I was working for UK companies before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within the first week, almost 40 recruiters contacted me with open positions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soon I realised I couldn't work for most of those companies for 2 reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not all jobs were fully remote. Some were hybrid (2-3 days a week in the office) or wanted to come to the office too often. That's a no go for me. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They were looking for an employee. They didn't want to do invoicing, so I'd have to be based in the UK., which I'm not.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I was left only with a handful of jobs where I was a viable candidate. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="search"&gt;Search&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#search" title="Permanent link"&gt;Permalink&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had to broaden my search to include other countries. I prepared two resumes, one for a Principal Engineer/Architect role and one for a developer. I searched for jobs, read descriptions and sent resumes a few hours a day, every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I applied to jobs where I didn't have all the skills. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's ok to do that. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They see your resume, and they decide if that's the problem. You need to admit during the interview what you know and what you don't and tell them you're keen to learn any missing skill. Over a few weeks, I applied to almost 60 jobs I found, and 144 recruiters contacted me with offers. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I replied to every single one of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Together I've sent over 150 resumes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="interviews"&gt;Interviews&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#interviews" title="Permanent link"&gt;Permalink&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this resulted only in 5 interviews.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In three of them, I was out in the 1st or 2nd round (or didn't hear back). The remaining interviews went better. Let's call these companies X and Z.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;X was three rounds, 5 hours of meetings and some homework where I had to do live coding, architecture presentation and whatnot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Z required me to build the app in the cloud with the backend and front end. It was about 6-8 hours of work and took me three evenings. It was two rounds and 2 hours of meetings. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are significant barriers to go through, but if you want a good job, you have to do the work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="offers"&gt;Offers&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#offers" title="Permanent link"&gt;Permalink&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got offers from both!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First from X: €100k+, 15% bonus and stock options. I told them to wait. I was waiting to see if I get an offer from Z. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I did: €130k+, no bonus, no stock options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I took Z for few reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I like what the company does.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's a new industry for me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They use things I never used before in production - CDK, React, TypeScript- you see, they hired me even though I don't know those things.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bonus is not guaranteed and  paid once a year, so it's not always money on the table.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stock options are only good if you're a very early employee or in a billion-dollar company. So it's not really a thing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#summary" title="Permanent link"&gt;Permalink&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finding a new job takes time and effort.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Send a lot of applications.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apply to jobs even if you don't have full qualifications.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take hard interviews that want you to do the work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be honest.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don't give up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Career"></category><category term="career"></category><category term="job"></category><category term="interview"></category></entry></feed>